and that i can say that it's my great
great pleasure to introduce today's
speaker inescipulito here in our ccnv
seminar series at the free university
in berlin where we have in this semester
as a topic of the seminar series
like
tutorials on the free energy principle
and predictive coding
and
some what was it half a year ago
inescipulita was also organizing here
big workshops that probably many people
have attended
on the free energy principle here in
berlin over the berlin school of mind
and brain
so ines
is affiliated to the
ucl in london
she is also a fellow at developmental
psychology at the faculty of the
behavioral science
faculty at the university of amsterdam
and is here in burden as lecturer at the
mind and brain school
which belongs to humboldt university and
is dealing in her work
as i understand it mostly with free
energy principle uh uh in the context of
interpreting the mind's function we had
multiple talks in the series before
which were
introducing mostly technical aspects of
free energy principle and computations
within that
we are very much looking forward to
your talk today
and
with this i think i
directly hand over nice to have you
thank you so much tim mohanda thank you
so much for uh inviting me um
joining uh these are wonderful um
speakers that i've been having in this
really great initiative group on the
financial principle in
in berlin
um thanks um so much for the very kind
introduction i am going to now try to
share my slides hopefully uh there won't
be any thing
rent access in systems preferences yes i
think that's fine
yeah so the title of my talk is the
financial principle on the edge of chaos
i would like to just preface it uh by
saying that um that uh it is a little
bit of a talk on um the
sorry on the the philosophy of science
of the french principle and that's sort
of like speaking to and relating to uh
the most recent uh events um on that
have been happening on the last year so
if you could just give me the next slide
perfect so yeah here we go um there's
been a little bit of a
discussion uh going on on the literature
on the philosophy side um people are um
talking to each other about
this realism non-realism uh kind of
approach um to the french principle of
course in philosophy this is not news um
it is a very uh live discussion in
philosophy of science in general about
theories models um
etc in in science in scientific practice
and more recently this uh debate has
been revived in the light of the french
principle and that's what i wanted to
talk about
today
so if you go to the next slide
yeah so um the lineup for today is just
these three main points uh i will go
very quickly over the realism debate and
then i will introduce just the
essentials of the free energy principle
which of course people that are uh usual
usually coming to these um to these
seminars of course uh they're very very
much acquainted but i'm going to
highlight the points that we need to
highlight in order to then come back and
think about the free energy principle in
the light of the realism debate
okay so um next slide yes so we go now
to the realism debate and uh
nobody would be happy with this uh
definition that i have here because uh
the realism debate is so nuanced uh
philosophically speaking that it will be
it is very difficult to come up with a
definition that will make everybody
happy but let's try um so we can say
about realism try to define it as uh the
properties of a model
are expected as
somewhat an ontological property of the
phenomenon of scientific interest so you
should find some kind of isomorphism
some kind of match between the
properties of the model and the
properties of
the phenomenon under study
the next
slide so for example the property of
study is as we are here precisely to
study all of that things that we love
the brain cognition or even
cell activity
next slide
yes so basically now there are three or
i was thinking about how can we uh put
this together the literature is so vast
and so integrated i was thinking okay
let's try to put together at least three
main groups or three main ways that we
can think of uh the realism
so the first one is uh the sort of like
the more traditional one which is
thinking about under realism thinking
about models as accurate representations
right and this comes for example from uh
go to freight
in sense and reference
next slide
yeah um so the second one is um a little
bit more complex uh but it's sort of
like what we have um we find a lot in uh
cognitive science or coming to
neuroscience which is uh the idea that
if models are obstructions
and if they succeed to predict
then the properties of the model should
be literally present
in the system being modeled
it was was there a question
oh i thought i had um a microphone okay
uh so you find for example that in uh
particularly uh very explicitly in uh
this paper by michael briscolora
defending a realist perspective on
bayesian cognitive science
next slide
the third way of being realist um
in scientific practice
is to claim um that claims made about
the system of interest of scientific
interest interest
by truth preservation can also apply to
the system itself
in which case a target system is health
to the properties of the model
so this is found for example in
these two papers that i have here which
are very recent in the literature
on the free energy principle and active
inference so that would be one way to
connect or think about models made under
active inference or free energy
principle uh that also hold a realist
perspective um
on on the target system explained under
the free energy or active inference
next slide
oh yeah so then um
what happens is to put it in a little
bit more of a simpler way is that
the mappings between the model and the
target so the mappings between the model
and the target allow to convert truths
found in the model into claims about the
target system so that's the very very
basic idea
that is being held in the this third
realist
assumption
and then we have the converse or the
counterpart anterialism
and roughly the definition
goes something like this the model is
simply an instrumental tool
that once applied to some activity of in
scientific interest
then the model allows to learn about and
draw predictions about a system of
scientific interest so the main
gist is that as opposed to having an
accurate
match or isomorphism by virtue of this
or that
way of thinking or arguing for it
the model is simply an instrumental tool
that is an opportunity for learning
next slide i think okay however
the system under study does not need to
have the properties of the model as of
course it is argued for
uh in the realist take on it right so
that's why
live debate going on next slide
okay so now also a couple of ways of uh
being anti-realist right
so the first one is the meaningless
way of thinking about models models are
in themselves meaningless
they do not hold semantic value other
than that that is constructed under or
by
using them to understand or predict
behavior and this was for example held
by uh david hilberg or um boss van
frassen
next slide oh yeah um
in the review models need not to be more
than empirically adequate
because they are mathematics um because
mathematics is arithmetic and algebraic
qualifier free identities so in this
sense models themselves are semantic
they do not hold any semantic value and
they are qualifier free
yep next slide okay
then uh very much in agreement with um
with uh david hilbert and uh blasphemy
is albert einstein in this amazing
lecture that he gave in berlin in 1921
if you hadn't have the opportunity to
read it please do so
and it tells us this was in berlin and
it tells us
as far as the laws of mathematics refer
to reality they are not certain
and as far as they're certain they do
not refer to the reality it is certain
that mathematics generally and
particularly geometry owes its existence
to the need which was felt of learning
something about relations of real things
to one another
so of course this is very much in line
with the anti-realism health by um david
hilbert um and van vlassen
next and i think i have something yeah
and this is actually something that if
you are interested on um i've just
alluded to in the paper is just out in
segmentary on michael miguel aguilera's
paper in physics of live reviews and we
do go on and a little bit on that casper
husband eye
okay next slide
anti-realism take two is that there is
found as uh models thought of as
idealizations or fictions
uh in science and the idea is that
models are
allow us to abstract certain features of
a phenomenon and they are for that
reason by virtue of abstraction and
opportunity for learning
next slide
then take three on anti-realism
is the view that the success of a model
justifies the acceptance of the
epistemic value of the model without
necessarily making ontological claims so
basically what we are saying is that um
the the virtue of the model resides in
its epistemic value and not in its
ontological commitments or ontological
commitments that one would make by
virtue of using a model
uh i think there's more on that slide
yeah the success of our best scientific
models um informed models um
even if our model is extremely
successful which of course we never know
because nobody would ever
claim that
they have a model that is true
in the best case scenario we would claim
that we have a model that is viable so
even if we have a very viable model
that does not according to this uh view
and andrew list view that does not allow
us to um
hold um a belief that everything in the
model is true so not even that the model
is viable
okay next slide
oh yeah so then we find these ideas for
example as far back as aussie under in
his introduction to um
copernicus magnus oppos
and it says something like this the
astronomer will take as their first
choice that hypothesis which is the
easiest to grasp
the philosopher will perhaps rather seek
the resemblance of the truth
but neither of them will understand or
state anything certain unless it has
been divinely revealed to them
now since one cannot in any way attain
the true causes
one will adopt whatever suppositions
enable the emotions to be computed
correctly
okay so this is taker three
the models are it's about the viability
of the models rather than the truthiness
of the models
okay so next slide
oh yeah so then um one last thought on
anti-realism um take three is that then
the hypothesis and assumptions
that may or may not be encoded in a
computational model are not intended to
describe the way the object being
modeled is actually structured but next
simply serve to represent the observed
data in an economical fashion and this
is quite interesting because these are
thoughts that weren't present quite
quite a while
a while back
in time okay next slide
so this was the setup uh of course he
did not do any justice um to the realism
debate which is absolutely rich super
nuanced but at least you got an idea of
like three takes of how to be realist
about models um or uh three ways of
being
non-realist or instrumentalist if you
will about models so now i want to say
something about the fep just
highlighting
points that i find interesting in order
to then come back to the realism debate
and think about the fep under that
realism debate and see what we make of
it
okay so then next slide all right so i
want to say here that i take um
typically i take my take on the fep
is um so there are these two ways that
you can get to the fep one is through
the low road which you start with
helmholtz um unconscious machine and
then you work your way through vision
inference until it gets to active
inference until you get to fep
my take on my preferable take is the
high road or what carl is called the
high road which is where you start with
biology and with certain observations
that you make in the behavior of the
world
and then you put forward a sort of like
first premise
um about as an attempt to start
explaining
how systems living systems adaptive
systems behave in the world in a way
that that first premise um explains uh
throughout across the board um adaptive
behavior so this is my preferred um way
i think it's though and that is most
plausible and most interesting to me
and it starts off with the question of
how is it that living organisms persist
while engaging in adaptive exchanges
with the environment
and this is an extraordinary thing
because
that's what i'm really obsessed about
and i really like is that it's so
extraordinary that you have an
environment that is constantly changing
so the only rule is that things change
um and yet living systems do not succumb
to those changes they actually persist
in this changing continuously changing
environment and this is the thought that
i find extremely important because
we should not lose sight of that thought
because once we do that will get us into
um other parts that i find at least i
find less interesting such as minds as
computers okay having said that um
next slide so this is living systems
maintain themselves by and then we
continue maybe we can just open the yes
by remaining in non-equilibrium steady
states right they are open systems which
is why as we all know the
non-equilibrium steady states and s
next one
and they do that by restricting
themselves to a limited
number of states and why is that well
because there is only a very a finite
number of states that will
keep them alive and um they will not um
attain a certain face boundary that
would
kill them or something like that okay
next one yeah
okay so then um the fvp coming from this
high road or described or explained from
this high road then
the first thing to bear in mind is that
it is a first principles in
statistical physics understanding where
organisms must maintain their existence
and this is what i was referring to
earlier on as that first premise so we
look at the world we look at
how living beings and adaptive systems
behave in the environment
right and there's one thing that is
common to these systems is that they
maintain their existence right and this
is nice to have as a first premise
because it's not um controversial at all
i don't think that anybody would um
dispute this
now the second step of the fep is that
how do they maintain their existence how
do they maintain this imperative well by
minimizing free energy which can be seen
or put forward or cast as computational
solution to the problem of explaining
how the systems maintain their existence
okay next slide
so then active inference becomes super
relevant here as we know because it is a
theory of how living organisms maintain
their existence so how they
comply with that imperative of remaining
alive maintaining their existence they
minimize surprise how via perception and
action yeah next slide
so then the first premise that we have
when we start off our understanding from
the fep
is that to survive
any living organism has to maintain
itself in a suitable set of preferable
or preferred states
while ever avoiding other
these preferred states of the
environment but then here another very
philosophical question comes up for the
philosophers in the room which is okay
but what are preferable states or prefer
states for a certain system how do we
define them how do they know right so a
bunch of
epistemological questions could come up
right and uh the fep does reply to that
um actually
okay so what are these preference states
right okay so preferred states are
composed of two important aspects so one
is
those that are defined by niche-specific
evolutionary adaptations
which for example
it would be very unlikely
to
find as we are doing our research for
example to find a butterfly in in a
river right because that would not be
good for the butterfly so those are
niche specific evolutionary adaptations
even though there was once a student of
mine who told me that some butterflies
like to go in the water so maybe this is
not a good example i should change this
example
okay um then the second
way of defining preferred states
is a very important one which is the
learned cognitive goals so as systems
interact with the environment of course
they learn much more about the
environment and themselves and that
would be the second way of setting or
determining what would be a preferred
state in order to maintain existence for
an adaptive system
okay next one
so in order to survive a fish for
example has stay in a comfort zone that
corresponds to a small subset of all
possible states in universe it has to
stay in water for example
yeah next
similarly a human has to ensure that the
internal states so for example the
physiological variables like body
temperature and heart rate remain within
acceptable ranges otherwise they will
die
so or they will become a corpse
next one
so then here i find this um
extremely um interesting uh for um
for for our perspective as human beings
because
uh if we do start with thinking okay
human beings need to maintain their body
temperature
so they need to do that by exerting
active control but then there are
different ways that we can do that as
opposed to non-human animals right so on
the one hand we can do and use all the
physiology such as sweating
but we can also um use some cognitive
mechanisms to buy a drink for example uh
non-human animals could for example look
for water
um or we can also have some cultural
practices like for example turning on
the air conditioning
just some examples
okay so then um the fvp or um principle
can be um thought of
as these sort of like steps where we can
think about active inference as the
biological problem of survival as
surprise minimization
uh where these surprising states are
those that are outside the comfort zone
of living organisms so for example a
surprising state for the butterfly would
be water and the surprising state for a
fish would be being outside of what
then the free energy principle i'm sorry
tender frenchy minimization comes very
handy because it is a practical and
biologically grounded way to explain how
adaptive systems minimize the price of
these sensory encounters with the world
okay next slide
then we can of course as we all know use
active inference precisely
to explain this coupling uh between a
system that is adapting to a
continuously changing environment where
we can have the system of interest as
internal states and the system with
which the the
and the surrounding environment of the
system as external states where as we
all know um internal and external states
do not directly influence one another
but they are indirectly influenced by
blanket states such as sensory and
active states and the nice thing about
it is that we
can use the markov blanket formalism
that is scale free which
interestingly allows us to
set up the internal states of scientific
interest um
for us
okay next slide yeah so then these
allows us if we want um and note that i
am doing literally the
higher road to the fep this allows us to
now
um think about or bring into the
conversation if we want the mechanistic
predictive processing explanation which
is derived from the fep describing
cognition as inference that aims to
diminish free energy so then what we
have is we have this mechanistic
explanation of a process theory that
allows us to explain uh the activity in
the brain in terms of this coupling
between internal and external states
being mediated by
by blankets and sorry by blanket state
um meaning uh
activity being explained by active
inference which then can be very much
translated to the language of the page
and brain hypothesis
okay next slide yeah which is uh very of
course uh known uh for us
um
as top-down processes that encode
predictions from priors and bottom-up
processes that encode sensory
observations such as prediction errors
so this like two
way uh trafficking um occurring uh in
brain activity and explaining how
brain activity works
okay next one
now um
this was the sort of like the high road
to the fvp and now i want to make like
some more highlights some points that i
find uh quite relevant um and
interesting in in in thinking about
things or behavior within the fep
framework or by putting in the fep
classes
so one evening when you do the whole um
top-down approach
or the high road approach to fep where
we start with um that
very very simple observation that
living beings adaptive systems
they want to maintain their existence
right even when we start with that and
then we find the fep and active
inference as a way of explaining how
they do that and then we arrive at
active inference and can translate all
the active inference formalism through
to predictive coding and explain how
things work
in the brain for example
it is important to note that even when
we do all of that trajectory
inference is not necessarily accurate
so the optimality of all these
mathematics and formalisms is subjective
in the sense that organisms operate on
the basis of
a subject's um or subjective uh
generative model of how the observer
observations are
generated
okay next one
so i find this picture in the active
inference book by pizzulo on and thomas
parr and carl um very very uh
interesting and useful to precisely
convey the point i want to make about
the generative model that i feel that
sometimes um we just don't um
don't see exactly um
how it uh really work or is its role is
so the genitive model um may be
optimized as a new experience is
acquired so think about that slide that
i have of how does a system how how
would we determine what would be the
preference stage to a system right
so
it's precisely through a generative
model that allows us to optimize um
a
model as new experience or new knowledge
is required right so then we have um for
example this picture here where you see
the difference between generative model
and a generative process i think i have
more things in this slide just
yeah okay so then we have this
distinction that should be made between
a generative model and a generative
process
and why so well because the genitive
model may or may not converge with the
generative process and that's sort of
what i wanted to highlight now
next way
yep so
the organism
the organism's model includes a range of
hypotheses about a hidden state
which doesn't do not necessarily include
the true value of the hidden state of
the generative process the generative
processes as you see here in the picture
the generative process is the world
right is how things are in the world
right undergenerative model is how i
think that things are right so um it
includes the way that i think that
things are in the world includes a range
of hypotheses about the world but those
hypotheses do not necessarily include
the true value of the world of the
generative process right um there's so
much many much of it yeah
so the models we use to explain our
sensorium may include hidden states that
do not exist in the outside world and
vice versa right so
in short what these means is that
there does not necessarily need to be
a isomorphic match between the
generative process and the generative
model right so that's the the gist here
next way
so this is where action becomes
extremely interesting and extremely
relevant because action is what is in
the middle between genetic model and
genetic process right so that's where we
get active inference um and what at
least i think uh is the the most
interesting thing in active inference
framework as opposed to other um
competing um explanations or frameworks
because action is generated on the basis
of the inferences made under a
generative model right but we just said
that the generative model does not
necessarily include the true state of
affairs of the generative process
but notably action is generated on the
basis of the inferences made under a
generative model
next yeah so action is
part of the generative process in the
sense of is it is through action that we
make changes in the world so action is
really that interesting thing that is
between the generative model and the
generative process action is generated
under the generative model which does
not necessarily match isomorphically
with the generative process and yet
action is what is influencing the
generative process action is what is
influencing the world
okay
so the the the interesting point here is
that despite action being selected from
the inferences drawn
under a model that is not necessarily
accurate as we said it is actually it is
this action that is going to affect the
generative process
okay next one
so action can be formulated as the
minimization of
the discrepancy between the generative
model and the genitive
process so it is not only that thing
that is sitting in the middle between
relative model and generative process
but it is actually what
can be used and is used to minimize the
discrepancy between generative model and
generative process
next one
so this is this were the points that i
uh wanted to make on the fvp and now i
want to get us back to think about the
fbp under the realism debate and see
whether there are some interesting
points or things to consider and think
about next slide okay so let's think
about the free energy principle
under the realism debate and let's think
about the free energy principle under
the option one of realism where the idea
was um so so so to say in the definition
was that models are accurate
representations okay
so if we think about um the fup and the
realism debate of the first option then
we would have to say that generative
models are inaccurate representations
because they do not necessarily
hold accuracy about the generative
process
so we could say that okay so then the
generative models are constructed under
the fep they are realistic
representations with some kind of form
of minimal form of realism some minimal
form of structuralism and similarity you
could say well they are genetic models
are representations of genitive
processes they're just not accurate
they're inaccurate representations and
they work so that could be one way um to
do that
and this is sort of what i think that um
kirchoff kiverstein and robertson uh
think in their paper but i would be also
keen to hear their thoughts about that
next
yeah so the reason that i say that is
because once we look at their paper in
the literalist fallacy and fep
model building scientific realism and
instrumentalism
um
so we saw before in one of the slides
when i was presenting realism debate
that one way of defining uh realism is
that the mappings within the model
no yeah the mappings within the model
and the target allow to convert truths
found in the model into claims about the
target system so in this case would be
the mappings between the fep model
allowed to convert truths found in the
fvp model into claims about the target
system which would be an adaptive system
then we find this for example no sorry
let me just
thank you and then we find for example
this passage in the paper
similarity we have argued for above
between the properties of the genitive
model and adaptive behavior such that
one can capture real statistical
relations in the world which is the
genitive process as we just said by
means of generative modeling so it seems
that in their paper that's precisely
where they're situated in the literature
which is precisely on the first name by
by realism where there is a similarity
between
the generative model and the generative
process but as we saw just now the
genitive model does not necessarily need
to be accurate about the generative
process next one
yeah which is precisely what i was
saying an organism's uh model includes a
range of hypotheses about a hidden state
which do not necessarily include the
truth value or the true value of the
hidden state of the generative process
that is not necessarily
an isomorphic
match of the model of the genetic model
and the genitive process or of the
organisms and the world right okay next
so then the second option would be the
anti-realist
option so what we said about generally
speaking we looked at three different
ways but what we said was that
generative models are empirically
adequate so we talked about oh they're
viable models um and uh not really true
models about um
scientific
phenomenon of interest they are
empirically adequate to the extent and
if they
allow us to learn more about the target
system
and if they allow us to make predictions
about the target system then they are
quite viable they're quite okay so
that's the entire list
view
and in the case of this uh anterior list
then representation or matching accuracy
is not an issue because models represent
in the way that they are used or we use
them to form or generate understanding
about a target system
next
yeah
okay
uh yeah
okay so this anti-realism would be um
this anti-realism about um fep would be
very much in line with for example this
brilliant work by albert einstein on
mathematics and geometry geometry and
experience they'll be perfectly aligned
because um
what what it says there is that well
models
are empirically adequate and this is
more or less and models will be more or
less adequate and um this is important
to define what we mean by adequacy right
that's the next question there will be
more and more or less adequate depending
not on accuracy so not on how much the
generative model
matches the generative process so not on
accuracy but on whether or not
it minimizes free energy so it is in the
sense of whether or not the model is
being used
allows the minimization of free energy
and much less on whether the model being
used matches the reality
so it's a little bit of a twist there um
next slide
so then then this non-realist fep uh
would also be uh very much in line with
for example
um complex and dynamical systems theory
because um as you know it says organisms
as complex systems that persist by
seemingly to define the second laws of
course they don't really literally defy
the second law of thermodynamics but
they seem to defy that law of
thermodynamics that
dictate or prescribe that they should
tend to dissipation or chaos but as we
observe behavior in the wild and in the
world we see that um
living organisms adaptive systems they
don't do that they don't persist to or
they don't succumb to the second law
right so they are extremely complex and
dynamic in the sense that their behavior
is quite adaptive and that's what makes
them so interesting so in this sense if
um our fvp models
are
virtuous not by virtue of them being
accurate in the sense that they
literally match isomorphically with um
genitive process but by virtue of
whether or not the model allows the
system to minimize free energy then
they'll be very much in line with the
complex systems theory
it would also be i believe in line with
an activism theory which i'm not sure if
everyone in the room is acquainted with
but um it's without there's been some
some attempts to make these links
between the fep and in activism and um i
think that
given other work that i've done um in
the past um i think that the only viable
way of really making this bridge um
logically sound
is through a non-realist fep
a realist fep uh is is much more harder
to argue for um uh
in their bridge or connection with
inactivism so but
i'm sure that more most of us are
acquainted with it um an activism states
that uh uh living beings enact the world
to adjust and adapt biologically
cognitively and culturally um to the
world
okay um next slide
yeah so then this is a very much um
it we've covered now the three points i
wanted to talk about
uh next slate
and i just want to conclude by sort of
like laying out what the options are for
us in this particular uh debate that has
become very lively debates in the last
one year or so so when we start from the
high road and this is important to
convey so it's not starting from the low
road it's starting from the high road so
when we start from the high road to the
fvp so when we start from the
observation of how biological systems
adaptive systems behave
and then we have
two
philosophy of science options which is
how do we model
these systems and how to think the
models by which we explain
living adaptive behavior okay so we can
take the realist take on it on our
models and say well um there is
realistic representations our models
literally
match
um isomorphically uh by different uh
philosophical strategies or arguments
they literally match uh
the behavior that we observe
and by the same reasoning we can also
say that the
organisms behaving in the wild they also
behave and adopt by virtue of possessing
models that literally match the world
around them
so that's one option
the other option is the anterior list
option which is to say that
the models that we as scientists have
the fep models as well as the models
that we as living beings have
um they allow us to
interact with the environment understand
the environment because they are
empirically adequate not because they
accurately represent uh the generative
process
so these are the two options uh that i
just wanted to highlight today i think
this is my last slide
yeah
okay thank you so much uh for your time
and uh of course i'm very much keen to
hear your all your thoughts and
questions